NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. 6174/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- PSPB 6/2/05, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  Agenda; draft minutes of March 23-24, 2005, meeting; memo re proposed certification regulations; draft of letter, with handwritten edits, to deputy education commissioner Johanna Duncan-Poitier, re teacher mentoring program, May 25; document, Recruiting and Retaining Quality Teachers in High Need Districts: A discussion and recommendation presented by the Professional Standards and Practices Board for teaching; list of PSPB members; executive summary of State Education Department Educational Leadership Certification Regulation, Goal 3, April 29
- PSPB 3/23/2005 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Agenda; May meeting agenda; draft minutes of January 20-21 meeting; paper for Education Policy Archives, "Catching Up With the Vaughn Express: Six Years of Standards-Based Teaching Evaluation and Performance Pay," by Eileen M. Kellor, University of Wisconsin-Madison, January 23, 2005; NYSUT Information Bulletin, "The Role of Mentor in District-Based Mentoring Programs," March 2005; document, Alternative Teacher Preparation Programs in New York State 2003-2004 Highlights, February 7, 2005 (statistics, charts and graphs); draft, Empire Promise Teacher Opportunity Corps
- PSPB January 20-21, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  Minutes of October 14-15 and November 18-19, 2004, meetings; booklet by National Education Association, Teacher Quality: Moving Forward (A Dialogue with the Teaching Commission: Teaching At Risk: A Call to Action), June 2004; memo to the Board of Regents from deputy education commissioner Johanna Duncan-Poitier re update on Educational Leadership Initiative, Goal 3, January 3, 2005; memo to Johanna Duncan-Poitier from NYSUT vice president Maria Neira re performance-based modifications re faculty staffing in teacher education programs, January 20, 2005; report, "Keeping Quality Teachers; The Art of Retaining General and Special Education Teachers: A Practical Guide for School Leaders Held Accountable for Student Success," 2004
- PSPB November 18-19, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  Agenda for PSPB Teacher Meeting; materials on 2004 legislative activity, how to lobby in 2005; NYSUT review and comment on State Education Department Draft Rubric for Assessing District Teacher Mentoring Programs 11/15/04; SED Office of School Personnel Review and Accountability Annual Part 83 Report, November 18, 2004; SED Report of the Mathematics Standards Committee, October 27, 2005; materials for nomination of 2006 New York State Teacher of the Year; draft document, Assessing the Development of Your District Teacher Mentoring Program, NY State Education Department Office of Teaching Initiatives, fall 2004
- Peer Intervention Program, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  Bound final report
- Public Schools see also Rise of Mass Public Schooling before 1914
- Public Schools for the 21st Century (PS21) Honor Roll Photo Exhibit 10/21/04, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  Invitation to event
- RMC Research Corporation, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Letter from Deputy Commissioner of Education James Kadamus to Maria Neira re RMC Research Corporation contract from the U.S. Department of Education to establish a regional center to help school districts meet the requirements of the No Child Left Behind Act of 2001, inviting Neira to nominate two classroom teachers to be members of advisory board, January 30, 2006; memo with names of teachers to serve on advisory board
- Radio Ad 10/18/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Script for public-service announcement for Maria Neira, urging parents to come to parent-teacher conferences
- Regents Candidates 2005 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Resumes of candidates David Ochoa and Howard M. Koenig, with cover letter from NYSUT president Richard Ianuzzi to Maria Neira indicating interest in Koenig, and related materials
- Regents Interviews 2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Questions by interview panel to Regent candidates; resumes of candidates Roger Bruce Tilles and Charles W. Fowler, with letter to NYSUT executive vice president Alan Lubin from president of the Nassau BOCES Central Council of Teachers (NABCOT), noting nomination of Fowler by Assemblyman Harvey Weisenberg, concurring with recommendation
- Regional Offices At-Large Directors Meeting 6/23/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Spreadsheet re costs to bring regional staff to NYSUT headquarters for meeting
- Regional Offices Capital District Regional Office Presidents Conference 2/3/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Draft remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; agenda
- Regional Offices Capital District Regional Office Staff Meeting 10/21/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Regional Offices Capital District Regional Office (CDRO) Regional Action Program (RAP), 2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  Summary of Regional Action Program; 2004-2005 RAP Activities for Cambridge, Averill Park, North Warren, Mohonasen, and Hadley-Luzerne teachers associations; list of participating teacher associations; cover memo to Executive Director for Field and Legal Services Pauline Kinsella, re CDRO staff assessments, year 3, April 4, 2005; description of Mohonasen Teachers Association Action Plan (MAP), with attached Action Plan Calendar
- Regional Offices Herkimer County Teachers Council Dinner 11/10/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; invitation to dinner; memo from Executive Vice President Antonia Cortese, soliciting recommendations for alternative compliance options and sanctions under Annual Yearly Progress requirement under No Child Left Behind, October 25; NYSUT press release praising SUNY Board of Trustees
- Regional Offices Nassau County 12/14/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; NYSUT press release re "great victory" in Campaign for Fiscal Equity
- Regional Offices Nassau Regional Office 11/30/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  Materials re meeting between Maria Neira and Mike Margolis
- Regional Offices North Colonie TA 5/4/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  Letter from North Colonie Teachers Association congratulating Maria Neira for election as First Vice President, inviting her to attend next meeting, with handwritten "yes"
- Regional Offices Southern Tier Regional Office (STRO) Spring Leadership Conference 3/17/06, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; program, for event; letter from AFT to all U.S. Senators, protesting record $3.5 billion cut in education funding in Bush administration FY 2007 budget, bringing to $55.7 billion the shortfall from what was promised for No Child Left Behind in the three years since the law was enacted, March 14; letter from AFT to U.S. Senators in support of amendment to increase Title I funding for FY 2007, noting cumulative gap of $40.3 billion (through FY 2006) between authorized and appropriated funding, March 15; agenda for NYSUT Education and Learning Trust training workshop, "Promoting Literacy for ELLs [English Language Learners, aka non-native speakers] at All Levels: A Training of the Trainers," March 18; State Education Department reports, "Overview of District Performance in English Language Arts, Mathematics, and Science and Analysis of Student Subgroup Performance for Sharon Springs Central School District," February 2005, "Accountability Status Report: English Language Arts, Mathematics, Science, and Graduation Rate for Sharon Springs CSD: 2004-05 Accountability Status: District in Need of Improvement Year 1 for English Language Arts," and Secondary-Level English Language Arts, March 6, 2006; newspaper clipping re sample questions appearing on state standardized math exam, lack of explanation for error, March 16, 2006
- Regional Offices Southern Tier Leadership Conference August 23-25, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  Agenda and materials for conference topic, "Employee Disciplinary Due Process Rights"; remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira
- Regional Offices Suffolk Leadership Conference 1/21/06, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Regional Offices Suffolk County Directors Meeting 10/25/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  Agenda; remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; report by Neira; materials re Labor-Religion Coalition
- Regional Offices Suffolk Regional Office 11/30/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  Memos re visit by Maria Neira
- Regional Offices Suffolk County 11/29/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; press release, "NYSUT Honors New York's XXX New Nationally Certified Teachers"; memo re meeting and agenda
- Regional Offices Syracuse Regional Office Workshop November 12-13, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  Draft remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; agenda; workshop participant list; list of VOTE/COPE (political action) contributions by local
- Regional Offices Ulster County Newly Tenured Teachers Reception 10/28/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira; edited draft
- Regional Offices Utica Regional Office Educational Conference 11/12/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  Agenda; evaluation form; handwritten opening remarks
- Regional Offices Watertown New Member Regional Workshop 10/27/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira
- Regional Offices Western NY Winter Leadership Conference 3/11/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 12/19/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  Agenda; proposal from Thirteen/WNET for event, The Celebration of Teaching and Learning; list of potential 2006 RA resolutions; resolution re state support for higher education
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 11/21/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  Agenda; list of planned meetings and discussion items for future NYSUT Policy Council, 2005-06; October Research Department manager's report; October Educational Services Department manager's report; School Finance and Policy Development progress report for October 2005
- Research and Educational Services Staff Meeting 11/18/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  Agenda; recommendations of Summer 2005 Planning Committee, August 17
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 11/07/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  Agenda; NYSU Information Bulletin re Classroom Teacher Salaries 2003-04
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 10/24/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 10/11/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  Agenda; 2006-07 Regents State Aid Proposal; list of responsibilities of NYSUT committees and task forces, staff
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 9/26/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  Agenda; agenda for NYSUT Policy Council meeting of October 12; related memo from Maria Neira
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 9/12/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  Agenda; overview summary of June 2005 Regents telephone surveys; agenda for Pre-COP meeting of September 14
- Research and Educational Services Staff Meeting 9/6/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  Agenda; recommendations of 2005 Summer Planning Committee, September 6
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 6/28/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  Agenda; Protocol for Resolving Disputes between Local Teacher's (sic) Union and Local School Districts Regarding Educational Programs Required by Statute, Regulation or Bargaining
- Research and Educational Services Staff Meeting 6/14/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  Summary of planning process for report by first vice president
- Research and Educational Services 6/6/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  Agenda; Final Report to the NYSUT Working Committee on Web Redesign, by CMS Watch, May 20
- Research and Educational Services Staff Planning Committee 5/31/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  Correspondence re setting up meeting; list of participant feedback from staff planning session
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 5/23/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  Agenda; 2005 committee nominations; letter of resignation for Policy Council member Donald Luisi; State Education Department report to Regents for discussion, "Policy Review of Early Childhood Education," February 23; letter from NYSUT president Richard Ianuzzi re support for UFT rally in Madison Square Garden on June 2
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 5/2/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  Agenda; program for New Local Presidents' Conference
- Research and Educational Services 4/18/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  New Board Orientation program, May 23; summary of public opinion research survey by Peter D. Hart Research Associates
- Research and Educational Services 4/4/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  Agenda; memo re computer installation
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 2/22/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  Agenda; NYSUT Information Bulletin re Role of the Union in Educational Programs
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 2/10/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  Agenda; January Research Department manager's report; January Educational Services Department manager's report; January monthly report of the Education and Learning Trust; School Finance and Policy Development Progress Report for January 2005; list of districts in need of improvement under Title I based on performance in 2003-04 school year; Education Daily highlights of President Bush's fiscal 2006 budget request; brochure by New York State Council of School Superintendents re workshop Assessments for Learning, March 31
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 1/19/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 12/20/04 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  Agenda; memo re retreat; NYSUT Policy Council agenda for January 12, 2004
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 12/7/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  Agenda; memo to NYSUT Board of Directors from Maria Neira re summary of major issues
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 11/23/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  Agenda; memo to local presidents from Maria Neira re NYSUT- Staples Partnership grant
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 11/11/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  Agenda; NYSUT Information Bulletin, "Report in the NYSUT Questionnaire for Presidents of Elementary and Secondary Teacher Locals, 2000-2001"; 2000-2001 Local Presidents' Phone Survey, January 2001; AFT QUEST workshop proposals; Toni Cortese Retirement List (programs and committees); Comments for SED Revisited Math Standards Survey
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 10/27/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 48)
- Research and Educational Services Staff Meeting 10/22/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  Agenda; list of those absent and reasons for not attending; handwritten notes re Kerry campaign
- Research and Educational Services Meeting 10/12/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  September Educational Services Department manager's report; September Research Department manager's report; September monthly report for the Education and Learning Trust; School Finance and Policy Development Progress Report for September 2004
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 5/21/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  Agenda; 2004 Local Presidents Conference summary of evaluations; NYSUT Committees 2004-05 Budget; NYSUT Research & Educational Services Staffing list
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting February 11-13, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  Agenda; January Educational Services Department manager's report; January Research Department manager's report; January monthly report for the Education and Learning Trust; School Finance and Policy Development Progress Report for January 2004
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 11/10/03, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  Agenda; October Educational Services Department manager's report; October Research Department manager's report; October monthly report for the Education and Learning Trust; School Finance and Policy Development Progress Report for October 2003
- Research and Educational Services Managers Meeting 10/27/03, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  Agenda; October Educational Services Department manager's report; September Research Department manager's report; September monthly report for the ETP; School Finance and Policy Development Progress Report for September 2003
- Retirement Events Jane Conetta Retirement Party 6/4/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  Invitation to dinner event honoring retiring Board of Directors member
- Retirement Events Toni Cortese Retirement Party 1/28/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  Invitation to event honoring AFT Executive Vice President Antonia Cortese
- Retirement Events Hobart Building Dedication 9/16/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 57)
- Retirement Events Hobart Building Dedication Meeting 5/12/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  Memos re meeting
- Retirement Events Tom Hobart Long Island Tribute 3/18/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  Invitation from Syosset Teachers' Association to event honoring retiring NYSUT president Tom Hobart
- Retirement Events Tony McCanns Retirement 6/22/06, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  Invitation to event honoring retiring teacher
- Retirement Events Stanley Rosengarten / Joseph Dixon Retirement Dinner 11/10/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  Invitation to event honoring Stanley Rosengarten and Joseph Dixon
- Retirement Legislation Passed Both Houses, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  Spreadsheet of NYSUT-supported legislation affecting NYS retirement plans
- The Rise of Mass Public Schooling before 1914 5/31/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  Copy of book chapter
- School Without Walls 9/14/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  Letter to Maria Neira from principal of School Without Walls, requesting a telephone conversation re Regents policy on NY consortium schools, September 14, 2005
- Carol Slotkin Conference Call 5/9/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  Correspondence with president of Sullivan West District local re difficult new superintendent, layoffs, with attached statement by Slotkin, The State of Our Union Pursuing Excellence is Union Work, April 26. See also ED 13 Mid-Hudson
- Social Security Interview 3/21/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  Questions and answers by Maria Neira re Bush plan to privatize/eliminate Social Security program
- Social Security Privatization, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  Questions and answers for Maria Neira re Social Security privatization; AFL-CIO flyers, "What Is Social Security?", "What You Should Know about Social Security Privatization," "Don't Believe the Spin," "What Privatizing Social Security Would Mean for Women," "What Social Security Privatization Would Mean to Young Workers," "What Privatizing Social Security Would Mean for African Americans," "What Social Security Privatization Would Mean for Latinos," "What Privatizing Social Security Would Mean for Public Employees," "What Privatizing Social Security Would Mean for Manufacturing Workers"
- Social Workers, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  Memos between Maria Neira and staff re draft reply to letter from social worker Steven Press about relationship between NYSUT and New York State School Social Workers Association, other issues
- Staples Partnership Grant Karen Smith, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  Confidential memo re investigation of Smith and Staples grant funds, September 16, 2005; end-of-project final report re Student of the Month Enrichment Program, by Karen Smith, September 1, 2005; letter to NYSUT executive assistant from City of New York Special Commissioner of Investigation for the New York City School District, requesting copy of cancelled check issued to Karen Smith, August 8, 2005; grant application from Karen Smith; related memos
- State Education Department see Commissioner Mills; see also Johanna Duncan-Poitier; see also James Kadamus; see also Mathematics Standards Committee
- Summer Intern Program, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  Memo re NYSUT sponsorship of Summer Intern Program for Undergraduate and Graduate students, primarily intended for children of NYSUT staff and activists
- Supplemental Educational Services 2/23/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  Correspondence re meeting; handwritten notes
- Teacher Aides see Para; see also AFT Paraprofessionals and School-Related Personnel Conference
- Teacher Awards see Disney Teacher Awards (Box 7)
- Teachers Program and Policy Council see AFT Teachers Program and Policy Council
- Teaching Assistants see Para; see also AFT Paraprofessionals and School-Related Personnel Conference
- Ron Thorpe see Widmeyer Communications
- Two Together, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  Memo to Pauline Kinsella, executive director of Field & Legal Services, describing Two Together, an after-school tutoring program in the Capital Region supporting literacy and language skills among elementary school children in Albany's South End, noting that regional staff director Linda Stanczik had been appointed to its Board of Directors. See also Capital Area Labor of Love
- Two Together Giffen School 04/22/07, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  Memo re "Cooks for Kids" event at Giffen School for after-school mentoring and tutoring program
- UUP Meeting 06/13/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  Letter to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira from William Scheuerman, president, United University Professions
- USNY (University of the State of New York) Summit on New York Education 11/2/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  Invitation to attend Summit on New York Education sponsored by the University of the State of New York and the Board of Regents, with attached confidential background and talking points, October 20; expected attendance list; agenda; Call for a Summit on New York Education; document, The Aims of the University: How Are We Doing Now?; presentation sheets re early childhood, key issues to close the performance gap; handwritten notes
- USNY Summit Regional Conversation 4/29/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  Agenda for USNY Summit Glens Falls Regional Conversation; letters to Maria Neira and Charles Santelli from Education Commissioner Richard Mills, thanking them for accepting invitation to attend, noting enclosed background papers
- USNY Summit Regional Meetings 2005 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  Agendas for meetings in Rochester, Syracuse, Long Island, Glens Falls, Hudson Valley, and NYC; related memo
- Vice Presidents Report December 2005 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  Report by Maria Neira
- Vice Presidents Report November 2005 (Box 7, Folder 79)
- Vice Presidents Report September 2005 (Box 7, Folder 80)
- Vice Presidents Report May 2005 (Box 7, Folder 81)
- Vice Presidents Report February 2005 (Box 7, Folder 82)
- Vice Presidents Report January 2005 (Box 7, Folder 83)
- Vice Presidents Report December 2004 (Box 7, Folder 84)
- Vice Presidents Report November 2004 (Box 7, Folder 85)
- Walmart: The High Cost of Low Prices 11/17/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  Flyer invitation to film preview, dinner, and reception at NYSUT headquarters
- Welcome to Kindergarten Debra Wing 2005 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  Preview material and order form for book Welcome to Kindergarten; correspondence between Maria Neira and author and kindergarten teacher Debra Wing
- Women of Color Union Leaders: Niki Dickerson Phone Interview 11/18/05, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  Correspondence to arrange interview between NYSUT vice president Maria Neira and Niki Dickerson, author of a book chapter on black and Latina women in the labor movement
- Widmeyer Communications Ron Thorpe Celebration of Learning December 13, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 89)
- Youth see Campaign for Youth
- John Zimmerman, Buchbinder Tunick and Company Meeting with Auditor 12/9/04, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  Draft consolidated financial statements, December 8, 2004; memo re meeting with John Zimmerman, outside auditor with Buchbinder Tunick & Co. to present overview of audit process